Thank you.
谢谢。
¶¶
¶¶
I love you.
我爱你。
Thank you.
谢谢。
All right.
好的。
Welcome back to the Ethereum Protocol Fellowship study group.
欢迎回到以太坊协议研究小组。
So, we are here today with our first session of the research track here with Dankrad to
因此，今天我们在这里与Dankrad的研究轨道第一届会议一起在这里
talk about some sharding and some data availability sampling.
谈论一些碎片和一些数据可用性采样。
So, Mario, I'll go ahead and let you introduce Dankrad for us, and then you can take it away.
所以，马里奥，我继续前进，让您为我们介绍Dankrad，然后您可以将其带走。
If you have slides or a screen share, Dankrad, you can do that with the little present button
如果您有幻灯片或屏幕共享，Dankrad，您可以使用“ Little Prander”按钮做到这一点
down there.
在那里。
Awesome, welcome, Dancred, and welcome all the attendees.
很棒，欢迎，舞者，欢迎所有与会者。
So it's a tough task to give introduction for Dancred, because it's a man who mostly
因此，为Dancred提供介绍是一项艰巨的任务，因为这是一个大多数人
needs no introduction, but I'll try anyway.
不需要介绍，但是我还是会尝试的。
So Dancred is joining us today, who is a researcher in Ethereum Foundation, as you probably know,
因此，Dancred今天加入我们，正如您可能知道的那样，他是以太坊基金会的研究员
which you might not know is that he is also, he's a background in theoretical physics from
您可能不知道他也是他，他是理论物理学的背景
Cambridge, which is very impressive.
剑桥，这是非常令人印象深刻的。
And he's been doing great work on cryptography and Ethereum, most famously the Dankshard
而且他一直在加密和以太坊上做得很好，最著名的是dankshard
Inc. and the data availability sampling, but also NPC-friendly proof of custody, development
Inc.和数据可用性采样，以及NPC友好的监护权证明，开发证明
of statelessness and related protocols for maybe like five years now.
无国籍和相关协议已经大概五年了。
So it's a real pleasure to have you here, Dankshard.
丹克沙德（Dankshard），很高兴能在这里到这里。
it's an honor to that you join our little study group and that we will hear
您加入我们的小学习小组是一种荣幸，我们会听到
about it
关于它
thanks for being from dunkard himself it's it's really great man so yeah
感谢您来自Dunkard本人，这是真的很棒的男人，是的
thank you so much for being here
非常感谢您在这里
yeah it can you hear us well I can hear you thank you
是的，你能听到我们的声音，我可以听到你谢谢你
the only thing is I'm I can't see a button to present right now
唯一的事情是我现在看不到一个按钮
So, in the, under the video, in the middle it says present, right?
因此，在视频下，在中间说出现，对吗？
No, I don't have a present button, I have mic, cam, chat, I don't have present.
不，我没有现在的按钮，我有麦克风，凸轮，聊天，我没有在场。
Is it maybe because I'm, yes I am, is it a problem?
是是因为我是的，是的，这是一个问题吗？
You probably need a desktop to be able to share the screen, but if you share your slides,
您可能需要一个桌面才能共享屏幕，但是如果您共享幻灯片，
I could.
我可以。
I'll do that, yeah.
我会那样做，是的。
Yeah.
是的。
Okay, I'll just send them on Telegram.
好吧，我只会通过电报发送它们。
Okay, it just gave me a second please.
好吧，请给我一秒钟。
So it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much
所以几乎这几乎是它的几乎是
it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's
几乎是它几乎是它的几乎是
pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty
几乎这几乎是它几乎很漂亮
much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much
几乎这几乎是它几乎是
it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's
几乎是它几乎是它的几乎是
pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty
几乎这几乎是它几乎很漂亮
much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's
几乎这几乎是它几乎是它的几乎是
much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much it's pretty much
几乎这几乎是它几乎是
Okay, perfect.
好的，完美。
Can you move them or...?
你可以移动它们还是...？
Yeah, I can see them.
是的，我可以看到他们。
Cool, cool.
酷，很酷。
Cool, so move to the next one.
很酷，所以移至下一个。
Yeah, so just to what I'm talking about today, so I want to start from blockchain scalability
是的，所以只是我今天所说的话，所以我想从区块链的可伸缩性开始
to introduce why we have to care about data availability.
介绍为什么我们必须关心数据可用性。
I'll move on to the data availability problem, talk about the solution in the form of data
我将继续解决数据可用性问题，以数据形式讨论解决方案
will be something, and then we'll be going more concretely into the tank sharding construction
将是某种东西，然后我们将更具体地进入坦克碎片结构
and also talk a bit about the EIP4844 that was implemented on Ethereum a couple of weeks
还谈论几个星期在以太坊实施的EIP4844
ago.
前。
Next slide, please.
请下一个幻灯片。
So, when we talk about blockchain scalability.
因此，当我们谈论区块链可伸缩性时。
So many years ago, Vitalik came up with the blockchain scalability trilemma.
这么多年前，维塔利克提出了区块链可伸缩性三元素。
What it says is that it is difficult to design a block chain.
它说的是很难设计一个块链。
it
它
provide
提供
Okay.
好的。
Hello? Hello. All right. That sounds better. Is it better? Good. Okay. I changed my internet
你好？你好。好的。听起来更好。更好吗？好的。好的。我改变了互联网
connection. Hopefully this will be better. Sorry for that. How far were you able to hear me?
联系。希望这会更好。对此很抱歉。您能听到我的声音多远？
Last thing I heard was Vitalik came up with the scalability trilemma.
我听到的最后一件事是，维塔利克提出了可伸缩性三元素。
Right, so the scalability trilemma says that it's difficult to design a blockchain that provides scalability, security and decentralization at the same time.
是的，因此，可伸缩性三元素说，很难设计一个可以同时提供可扩展性，安全性和权力下放的区块链。
And the important thing here is it doesn't say that it's impossible.
重要的是，它并不是说这是不可能的。
Just back when Vitalik came up with this, we didn't really have all the constructions that were needed to make a scalable blockchain.
就在维塔利克（Vitalik）提出这一点时，我们并没有真正拥有制造可扩展区块链所需的所有构造。
But luckily, we do have them now, and I'll talk today about one of the important components of this solution.
但幸运的是，我们现在确实有它们，我今天将讨论该解决方案的重要组成部分之一。
If you can go to the next slide.
如果您可以去下一个幻灯片。
So let's talk about one of the parts here of the state trilemma, which is decentralization.
因此，让我们谈谈国家三元组的部分，即权力下放。
So, when we talk about decentralization, what we mean is, importantly, one important thing
因此，当我们谈论权力下放时，我们的意思是，重要的是一件重要的事情
that we want is that it is pretty easy for anyone to run a node.
我们想要的是，任何人运行节点都非常容易。
And this is what makes decentralization difficult.
这就是使权力下放的原因。
So, next slide.
所以，下一个幻灯片。
If we look at this node here, ideally, we want that someone can easily run a node in
如果我们在这里查看此节点，理想情况下，我们希望有人可以轻松地运行一个节点
their own home.
他们自己的家。
This importantly means that two factors are limited.
重要的是，这意味着两个因素是有限的。
One is execution.
一个是执行。
This little box that anyone can buy for ideally at most a few hundred dollars is limited in
这个任何人都可以购买理想的小盒子最多只有几百美元。
how much it can do.
它可以做多少。
Also, we want the user potentially to still be able to use it for other things at the
另外，我们希望用户可能仍然能够将其用于其他事项
same time.
同时。
So we don't even want to use the CPU full time.
因此，我们甚至不想全职使用CPU。
And the second thing is the bandwidth.
第二件事是带宽。
So like the internet connection that a person can get
因此，就像一个人可以得到的互联网连接一样
in their home is typically limited
在他们家中通常有限
depending on the country.
取决于国家。
And so we have to be happy with like what we can get there
因此，我们必须对我们能够到达那里的东西感到满意
and that further limits how much one node can perform.
这进一步限制了一个节点可以执行多少。
Next slide.
下一个幻灯片。
So if we look at the blockchain stack it's like from our modern understanding, we see
因此，如果我们看一下区块链堆栈，就像我们的现代理解一样，我们会看到
it as having like four different layers and those layers are execution, settlement, data
它具有四个不同的层，这些层是执行，结算，数据
availability and consensus.
可用性和共识。
So consensus is just like it's basically how do we know which one is the chain that we
因此，共识就像是基本上是如何知道我们哪一个是我们的链
all agree on like how do we come come to agreement on what's the what is the latest block and um
所有人都同意，例如我们如何就最新的区块和UM达成共识
that's like things like proof of work and proof sake play a role here data availability um is the
就像工作证明和证明清酒之类的事情在这里起作用数据可用性um是
one as the part i'm talking about today which is like um how do we know that everything that um
一个作为我今天所说的部分，就像嗯，我们怎么知道一切
that was part of the blockchain is available to everyone settlement um is the layer is
那是区块链的一部分，每个人都可以解决，um是该层是
it's the settlement layer which means basically it's it's the it's the root layer of um all the
这是沉降层，这基本上意味着它是UM的根层
for example assets on a chain so it's kind of the logic that everything goes back to and that
例如，链上的资产，因此一切都可以恢复到的逻辑
tells you like okay this is um this is who this um eth or erc20 token belongs to right now and
告诉你喜欢好的，这是这个um eth或erc20 soken现在属于的人，
execution is the layer that decides which transactions are valid um so execution is
执行是确定哪些事务有效UM的一层，因此执行是
is the layer that says, if you execute this transaction,
是说，如果您执行此交易，
then the accounts change in this way,
然后帐户以这种方式更改，
or they don't change because it was an invalid transaction.
或者它们不会改变，因为这是一项无效的交易。
And if we go to the next slide, so two of these layers
如果我们去下一个幻灯片，那么其中两个层
are actually inherently settlement and consensus.
实际上是天生的解决和共识。
They do not really depend on the number of transactions
他们并不真正取决于交易的数量
that our blockchain has to process.
我们的区块链必须处理。
So consensus does not depend on it because consensus can come, we can come to consensus
因此，共识不依赖于此，因为共识可以得出，我们可以达成共识
on things like hashes.
关于哈希之类的东西。
So we can very highly compress the amount of data that we have to come consensus on.
因此，我们可以高度压缩必须达成共识的数据量。
So actually consensus doesn't really care if we have one transaction per second or a
因此，实际上并不真正在乎我们每秒进行一项交易还是
million.
百万。
And for settlement, this is true in a similar way.
为了解决，这是类似的方式。
We don't always need to settle every single transaction immediately.
我们并不总是需要立即解决每笔交易。
We can basically net large numbers of transactions.
我们基本上可以净数量的交易。
And so settlement doesn't necessarily depend on the number of transactions either.
因此，解决方案也不一定取决于交易的数量。
But the two things that do absolutely depend on the number of transactions are data availability and execution.
但是，这两件事绝对取决于交易的数量是数据可用性和执行。
Data availability, because we need to have the data for every single transaction available to anyone who wants it,
数据可用性，因为我们需要为所有想要的人提供每笔可用的数据，
or at least anyone who needs it to know whether,
或至少有人需要它知道是否
whatever they're depending on, for example,
无论它们取决于什么，例如
the balance of their account is valid.
他们帐户的余额有效。
And execution, similarly, like we need,
和执行一样，就像我们需要一样
yeah, we need currently, for example,
是的，例如，我们目前需要
on Ethereum to execute all the transactions,
在以太坊上执行所有交易，
and so it also requires to scale
因此，它也需要扩展
with the number of transactions.
与交易的数量。
Next slide.
下一个幻灯片。
And so, a few years ago, we came up with the idea of so-called roll-ups.
因此，几年前，我们提出了所谓的卷起的想法。
And this was finally, like previously, there were many different ideas for scaling blockchains
终于，就像以前一样，有许多不同的想法来扩展区块链
like state channels, which are implemented on Bitcoin, for example, known as Lightning,
例如，在比特币上实现的状态渠道，例如，称为闪电，
Plasma, and others.
等离子体和其他人。
But all of these have pretty severe limitations on what they can do, and they didn't really
但是所有这些都对他们能做什么有很大的限制，而且他们并没有真正
provide all the things that we want on Ethereum, especially universal computation.
提供我们想要的所有内容，尤其是通用计算。
But with rollups, we finally came up with a way to universally scale computation.
但是随着汇总，我们终于提出了一种普遍扩展计算的方法。
And they get their scalability from either fraud proofs or validity proofs, also colloquially
他们从欺诈证据或有效性证明中获得了可扩展性，也通俗地
known as zk and in this way they can prove to all the nodes that transactions were wallet
被称为ZK，这样他们就可以向所有节点证明交易是钱包
valid without them actually having to verify every individual transaction so that's where
有效而无需它们实际上必须验证每个单独的交易，所以这就是
the scaling comes from we need somehow to stop like every node having to execute all the transactions
缩放来自我们需要以某种方式停止，就像每个节点必须执行所有交易一样
next slide and then the final part of this is how do we scale data availability and that's what i'm
下一个幻灯片，然后最后一部分是我们如何扩展数据可用性，这就是我
going to talk about today and the solution to that is data availability sampling.
今天要谈论的是数据可用性采样。
Okay let's talk a bit about the data availability problem. So the definition of the
好的，让我们谈谈数据可用性问题。因此
data will improve it means that no network participant and that includes a colluding
数据将改善它意味着没有网络参与者，其中包括勾结
super majority of full nodes has the ability to withhold data. So the important part is that
超级全节点的超级节点具有扣留数据的能力。因此，重要的是
This includes the colluding supermajority.
这包括勾结的超级差。
So data availability is actually relatively easy to solve if, for example, you say, like,
因此，如果例如，您说，数据可用性实际上相对容易解决
oh, I'm willing to trust that the majority of Ethereum validators are always honest.
哦，我愿意相信大多数以太坊验证者总是诚实的。
And in that case, you could simply, like, make them all vote on it.
在这种情况下，您可以简单地，就像使它们全部投票。
And if they vote for it, then the data is available.
如果他们投票赞成，那么数据可用。
And that is always true as long as they are honest.
只要诚实，这总是正确的。
But that's not enough for, like, blockchains like Ethereum.
但这还不足以像以太坊这样的区块链。
we want the type of security that goes beyond just trusting a majority.
我们希望不仅仅是信任大多数的安全性。
We want that things like the validity of all transactions on the chain can be independently verified
我们希望可以独立验证链上所有交易的有效性之类的东西
and have nothing to do with whether the validators are honest.
与验证者是否诚实无关。
So the power of the validators in Ethereum is fairly limited,
因此，以太坊中验证者的力量相当有限，
and this is an important property that we want to preserve.
这是我们要保留的重要财产。
And this data availability is solved in current blockchains.
并且该数据可用性在当前区块链中解决。
including Ethereum, with so far only one exception, or two exceptions, by all full
包括以太坊，到目前为止，只有一个例外，或两个例外
nodes downloading all the data. So currently, Ethereum nodes, whenever there's a new block,
下载所有数据的节点。因此，目前，以太坊节点，每当有新块时，
all the nodes receive the new block, and therefore, they know the block is available,
所有节点都会收到新块，因此，他们知道该块可用，
because they've seen it. They've literally seen the whole block.
因为他们看过了。他们从字面上看了整个障碍。
And so the question is, how do we make this scalable? So scalable means that
因此，问题是，我们如何使此扩展？因此可扩展意味着
the work required should be less than downloading the full block. And more specifically, we want
所需的工作应小于下载完整块。更具体地说，我们想要
something like constant or maybe a logarithmic amount of work, like a square root tends to
诸如常数或对数的工作量之类的东西，例如平方根倾向于
already be a lot. So that's kind of our goal. Next slide. And so I like to
已经很多了。这就是我们的目标。下一个幻灯片。所以我喜欢
to talk a bit more about data availability
谈论数据可用性
because it's very often confused.
因为它经常感到困惑。
So data availability, what it does mean is that
因此，数据可用性，这意味着
the assurance that the data was not withheld.
保证数据没有被删除。
So it's the assurance that the data was published.
因此，这是发布数据的保证。
This is the important part.
这是重要的部分。
Next slide.
下一个幻灯片。
What it does not mean, what it's not data availability
这不是什么意思，它不是数据可用性
is data storage.
是数据存储。
Data storage is 10 years later, you can ask, hey, what was the data then?
数据存储是10年后，您可以问，嘿，那是什么数据？
This is a separate property that you can also want, but importantly, it's not data availability.
这是您也可能想要的单独属性，但重要的是，这不是数据可用性。
So this is data storage or continued availability.
因此，这是数据存储或持续可用性。
And I'm not talking about that.
我不是在谈论这个。
This is also something you might want.
这也是您可能想要的。
Luckily, it's actually much easier to achieve that data availability.
幸运的是，实现数据可用性实际上要容易得多。
This does not require as complicated constructions often, because as soon as the data is published, you only need one person in the world to preserve it.
这不需要经常复杂的结构，因为一旦发布数据，您只需要世界上一个人来保存它。
One person in the world is enough to always get that data.
世界上的一个人足以始终获取数据。
Whereas if the data wasn't published in the first place, then that honest person doesn't help you because they never receive the data.
而如果首先发布数据，那么那个诚实的人就不会为您提供帮助，因为他们从未收到数据。
So that's why data availability is so much harder to achieve than data storage.
这就是为什么数据可用性比数据存储更难实现的原因。
Okay, so this data-valued problem, to many, when they first hear about it, it sounds like
好的，所以这个数据值的问题对许多人，当他们第一次听到它时，听起来像是
an unimportant detail.
一个不重要的细节。
It's just some annoying detail in many scaling solutions, which we actually found many times.
在许多扩展解决方案中，这只是一些令人讨厌的细节，我们实际上已经找到了很多次。
Often people thought about, for example, Plasma, it was for a long time thought of being the
人们经常想到，例如等离子体，很长一段时间以来，
ultimate scaling solution.
最终缩放解决方案。
In the end it turned out it hits like big problems and this was part of it that it didn't
最后，结果发现它像大问题一样命中，这是其中的一部分
have data availability.
具有数据可用性。
And so why is it so important?
那为什么这么重要呢？
So we have two options for getting fully scalable universal execution.
因此，我们有两个选择可以完全可扩展的通用执行。
And one of them is optimistic roll-ups which use fraud proofs.
其中之一是使用欺诈证据的乐观卷起。
So the way they work is you post batches and make a claim that a new stage route is the correct stage route after executing the transaction.
因此，他们的工作方式是您发布批处理，并声称新的舞台路线是执行交易后正确的舞台路线。
And after that, anyone can submit a fraud proof claiming that this is not the correct result.
之后，任何人都可以提交欺诈证据，声称这不是正确的结果。
And then they play out a little game which has the property that whoever's right can always win the game if they play the correct strategy.
然后他们玩了一个小游戏，该游戏的财产是，如果他们玩正确的策略，任何人都可以始终赢得比赛。
And this is really cool.
这真的很酷。
it only has one catch what if whoever committed the fraud didn't publish the data they just
只有一个人只有一个人，如果谁犯了欺诈的人没有发布他们的数据
managed to somehow get the state root on chain but without publishing the data
设法以某种方式将状态扎根在链上，但没有发布数据
well now you have the problem that you cannot create the fraud proof because people might know
好吧，现在您遇到了无法创建欺诈证据的问题，因为人们可能知道
well no this can't be the correct result but they can't prove it so like for example like
好吧，不，这不能是正确的结果，但是他们不能证明这一点，例如
my example here is there could be like one tiny transaction there it could be literally like this
我在这里的例子是，那里可能会有一笔微小的交易，从字面上看
why you can't even miss a tiny bit of data and it just like prints one trillion ether and
为什么您甚至都不会错过一小部分数据，就像打印1万亿以太一样
if you can't uh like you can't prove the fraud then this would happen on the roll up
如果您不能像无法证明欺诈行为一样，那将发生在卷中
obvious it wouldn't really affect ethereum itself because that would still be contained on that roll
显然，它不会真正影响以太坊本身，因为那仍然包含在该卷中
up um but like it would still be a huge problem for for the roll up and like everyone else would
嗯，但是就像滚动一样，这仍然是一个巨大的问题，就像其他所有人一样
would now not be able,
现在无法
like someone just can exit all this ether
就像有人可以退出所有这些以太
or however much the rollup had locked up
或多大的汇总已锁定
and everyone else would not get anything.
其他所有人都不会得到任何东西。
So we need really all data to be available unconditionally,
因此，我们实际上需要所有数据才能无条件可用，
otherwise fraud proofs cannot be constructed.
否则将无法构建欺诈证据。
For zk-rollups it's more subtle than that.
对于ZK滚动，它比这更微妙。
Like for rollups, for optimist rollups
像汇总一样，用于乐观主义者汇总
it's really obvious why you need that.
这真的很明显。
For zk-rollups you could ask,
对于您可以问的ZK滚动，
well, I mean, even if the data's missing,
好吧，我的意思是，即使数据丢失，
nobody can ever really completely
没有人真的可以完全
make fraudulent transaction because you always have to prove correctness
进行欺诈交易，因为您始终必须证明正确性
but there's like this annoying thing which is like basically when you have money in your account
但是像您在帐户中有钱的时候基本上一样
um in order to access it you need to prove that you have that money
嗯，要访问它，您需要证明您有钱
and you cannot do that if you don't have the witness or maybe you don't even don't know how
如果您没有证人，或者也许您甚至不知道如何
much money it is exactly because someone made a dust transaction into your account.
这正是因为有人将灰尘交易纳入您的帐户。
And basically, yes, your money is there.
基本上，是的，您的钱在那里。
Like nobody can steal it, so to speak, from your account, but they can kind of just lock
可以这么说，就像没有人可以从您的帐户中偷走它，但是他们可以锁定
it up there and then they can blackmail you.
它在那里，然后他们可以勒索您。
Obviously, I can say, well, I'll give you the witness, but you have to give me 50 percent
显然，我可以说，好吧，我给你证人，但是你必须给我50％
of your money.
你的钱。
So even for ZK rollups where you can never have invalid transactions on chain, you actually
因此，即使对于您永远无法在链上进行无效交易的ZK汇总，您实际上也
need data availability.
需要数据可用性。
And this brings us to data availability sampling.
这使我们可以进行数据可用性采样。
So the idea behind data availability sampling
因此数据可用性采样背后的想法
is as follows.
如下。
Instead of, like, we took our data here
我们不像一样，在这里获取数据
and I've, like, basically chunked it up
而且我喜欢基本上把它分解了
into these D0 to D9 little chunks.
进入这些D0到D9小块。
And the idea would be that what we want to do
这个想法是我们想做的
is instead of downloading all the data,
而不是下载所有数据，而是
we just select some random bits of it
我们只选择一些随机位
and just download those.
然后下载这些。
And we could hope that, well, if all of those that we request are available, then all the data is hopefully available.
而且，我们可以希望，好吧，如果我们要求的所有这些都可以使用，那么所有数据都希望可以使用。
Right. But, next slide, please.
正确的。但是，请下一个幻灯片。
There's one little catch, which is that if any data is missing that we happen to not sample, we literally don't detect it.
有一个小问题，那就是，如果缺少任何数据，我们碰巧没有采样，我们实际上不会检测到它。
And the problem, as we discussed before, is that unfortunately, on blockchains, even a tiny bit of data missing can be completely catastrophic because we have this important financial information.
正如我们之前讨论的那样，问题在于，不幸的是，在区块链上，即使是一小部分数据丢失也可能完全是灾难性的，因为我们拥有这些重要的财务信息。
And yeah, unfortunately, the missing transaction could be printing 1 trillion Ether.
是的，不幸的是，丢失的交易可能是打印1万亿以太。
And if we miss that, then we're just fucked.
如果我们错过了那个，那我们就被操了。
And so we cannot afford even one bit of data missing.
因此，我们甚至无法负担得起一点点数据。
And so this simple idea doesn't directly work.
因此，这个简单的想法无法直接起作用。
We can't just split up the data into chunks.
我们不能仅仅将数据分成块。
So here's an example.
所以这是一个例子。
If we say our client samples 10% of the data,
如果我们说我们的客户样本的数据的10％，
it's just quite a lot, right?
这只是很多，对吧？
Then the block producer could hide a single unavailable transaction.
然后，块生产商可以隐藏一个不可用的交易。
Now, we know that catching this one transaction,
现在，我们知道，抓住这项交易，
the probability for that is 10%,
概率为10％，
because that's how much data we're sampling.
因为那是我们采样的数据。
But that's not a great, those aren't great odds,
但这不是一个伟大的，那不是很大的机会，
it's just 10% of catching like an attacker
像攻击者一样，只有10％
who's trying to hide some important data.
谁试图隐藏一些重要的数据。
And we already like sampling 10% of the data.
而且我们已经喜欢对10％的数据进行采样。
So the trade-off here doesn't really work.
因此，这里的权衡实际上并不奏效。
So this brings us to the idea of erasure coding the data.
因此，这使我们想到了删除编码数据的想法。
So what we do instead is we don't just
所以我们做的不仅仅是我们不只是
take the original data.
获取原始数据。
So like here, we have now four chunks of original data,
因此，像这里一样，我们现在有四个原始数据，
D0 to D3, but instead we add some extra data to it.
D0至D3，但我们为其添加了一些额外的数据。
We like add a so-called erasure codes.
我们喜欢添加所谓的擦除代码。
And in this example it's specifically read Solomon code.
在此示例中，它专门读取所罗门代码。
What that means is we take the original data,
这意味着我们采用原始数据，
we interpret the data as points on a polynomial,
我们将数据解释为多项式上的点
And then we can extend it, like if we have four points on a polynomial,
然后我们可以将其扩展，就像我们在多项式上有四个点一样，
we know that we can always interpolate it into a unique polynomial of degree 3.
我们知道，我们总是可以将其插入第3度的独特多项式中。
And we evaluate that at four more points.
我们在另外四个点评估了这一点。
These are E0 to E3.
这些是E0至E3。
And now we have this really cool property of polynomials that says
现在，我们拥有多项式的这种非常酷的属性
if you have any D plus 1 points of a degree D polynomial,
如果您有任何D加1点D度多项式，则
you can always interpolate the polynomial, and it's unique.
您总是可以插入多项式，并且它是唯一的。
So this means that if I have D0, D3, E1, and E2, for example,
因此，这意味着，如果我有D0，D3，E1和E2，例如
then from that I can reconstruct it,
然后我可以重建它，
and I will get back all the same points.
我会回到所有相同的观点。
And this is no matter which subset of points I take.
无论我提到哪个子集。
Right.
正确的。
And so this is really cool,
所以这真的很酷，
because now this original idea of sampling actually becomes efficient.
因为现在这种采样的原始想法实际上变得有效。
So as an example, if we take 30 random chunks, and all of those are available, then the probability
因此，例如，如果我们进行30个随机块，并且所有这些都可用，则概率
that 50% of the data is unavailable is only two to the minus 30.
50％的数据不可用的是减去30。
That's one in a billion.
那是十亿分之一。
So that's pretty low.
所以这很低。
So this is a huge difference to what we had before, right?
因此，这与我们以前拥有的巨大不同，对吗？
We now just query 30 chunks, and that's a constant number.
现在，我们只是查询30个块，这是一个恒定的数字。
So it doesn't matter.
所以没关系。
It doesn't have to be 10% of the data.
不必是数据的10％。
If we have 3,000 chunks, then it's 1% of the data.
如果我们有3,000个块，则是数据的1％。
If we have 30,000 chunks, it's 0.1% of the data.
如果我们有30,000个块，则是数据的0.1％。
So it's constant.
所以这是不变的。
And the probability is now really low, and we can make it lower.
现在的概率确实很低，我们可以使其降低。
If we do 40, then we have $100 trillion.
如果我们做40，那么我们有100万亿美元。
So it quickly becomes an extremely low statistical event.
因此，它很快成为一个极低的统计事件。
But there's one catch to this, which is that, quick correction, this is right.
但是，有一个捕捉，也就是说，快速更正，这是正确的。
This should say degree three, not five.
这应该说三学位，而不是五位。
But that's fine.
但这很好。
So basically what could happen is that these extension points were not computed correctly,
因此，基本上可能发生的是这些扩展点未正确计算，
that an attacker just makes up random points or whatever.
攻击者只是构成随机点或其他任何东西。
And now what happens is that if you have any 50% of these points, you can interpolate it,
现在发生的是，如果您有50％的要点，则可以插入它，
but each of these interpolations will be different.
但是这些插值中的每一个都会有所不同。
And that's clearly bad because, I mean, the most important property of blockchain is always
这显然很糟糕，因为我的意思是，区块链最重要的特性总是
that everyone agrees on the same thing.
每个人都同意同一件事。
So we cannot afford this.
因此，我们负担不起。
And so we need a way of ensuring that whatever is in a block is always a correct read Solomon
因此，我们需要一种确保块中的任何内容始终是正确的读所罗门的方法
code, or in other words, that the whole thing is a pretty normal of the correct degree.
代码或换句话说，整个事情都是正确程度的正常。
And this is where we use something really cool, which is so-called KCG commitments,
这就是我们使用真正酷的东西，即所谓的KCG承诺，
which are a type of polynomial commitments.
这是一种多项式承诺。
And KCG commitments have the property that they always commit to a polynomial, and you
KCG承诺具有他们一直致力于多项式的财产，而您
can limit the degree of that polynomial.
可以限制该多项式的程度。
So you can say, like, this root has to be a commitment to a polynomial of degree three.
因此，您可以说，这根根必须是对三级多项式的承诺。
And what this means is that we automatically get the property that whatever anyone, whether it's an honest note or an attacker, commits to is always a polynomial of the given degree.
这意味着我们会自动获得任何人的财产，无论是诚实的笔记还是攻击者，都承诺始终是给定学位的多项式。
And so it's not possible anymore to commit to an invalid root.
因此，不再可能致力于无效的根源。
And this is like this array nest discovery
这就像这个数组巢发现
that we made a few years ago
几年前我们做了
and that's finally made it possible to implement.
最终使实施成为可能。
And luckily it has become very efficient
幸运的是，它变得非常有效
over the last few years.
在过去的几年中。
Cool.
凉爽的。
So let's go into the DAG charting construction
因此，让我们进入DAG图表结构
that I came up with a little bit more than two years ago.
我想出了两年多前提出的。
So let's talk about what sharding originally looked like, or what many people imagine it
因此，让我们来谈谈碎片最初是什么样的，或者很多人想象的
as, what it would be like on Ethereum.
因为，在以太坊上会是什么样。
So the idea was that, so we always had like this beacon chain plus later, like we added
所以想法是，所以我们总是像这款信标连锁链和后来一样，就像我们添加的那样
the execution blocks to that.
执行阻塞。
And then the idea was that in parallel to that beacon chain, there would be many shards,
然后的想法是，与那条灯塔链并行，会有很多碎片，
originally it was like 1024 different shots all running in parallel and similar to the beacon
最初就像1024个不同的镜头，所有镜头都并行运行，类似于信标
chain each of them would have a proposer and then each of them would have a committee that votes on
连锁他们每个人都有一个建议者，然后每个人都将有一个投票的委员会
whether that proposer showed up and what block they proposed
该提议者是否出现以及他们提出了什么障碍
and um so the question is why why was that necessary why do we need all this like all
嗯，所以问题是为什么我们为什么需要所有这些都需要所有这些
all these committees in here.
所有这些委员会在这里。
While the problem is that each of these proposals
虽然问题在于这些建议中的每一个
can do something bad.
可以做一些不好的事情。
Each can like not publish their data
每个人都可以不发布他们的数据
or each of them can,
或他们每个人都可以
each of them can like publish two different blocks
他们每个人都可以发布两个不同的块
at the same time.
同时。
And that has important consequences
这有重要的后果
because now the next problem is
因为现在下一个问题是
these committees can be split.
这些委员会可以分解。
Like what if, sorry, stayed the same idea.
喜欢，对不起，请保持同样的想法。
These committees could just be 50-50.
这些委员会可能只有50-50。
And, well, then you have a problem.
而且，那么，您有一个问题。
Then how do you decide which one was the right one?
那么您如何确定哪个是正确的？
And so this meant that essentially we have to wait for a long time for these committees to confirm.
因此，这本质上意味着我们必须等待很长时间才能确认这些委员会。
And it could take several epochs until you knew what each chart block does.
并且可能需要几个时期，直到您知道每个图表块的作用。
And when you start going through that design, you notice that that brings along with it a lot of problems in practice.
而且，当您开始进行该设计时，您会注意到这带来了许多实际问题。
Like, for example, I mean, just to mention one of them, imagine you are a roll up and you want to publish your blogs, but they don't get confirmed.
例如，我的意思是，只要提到其中一个，想象一下您是一个卷起，您想发布自己的博客，但没有得到确认。
And now what are you going to do? Are you going to publish the next blog? Are you going to republish it in case it doesn't get confirmed and so on?
现在你打算做什么？您要发布下一个博客吗？您是否要重新发布它，以防其确认等等？
So it's actually really difficult. And I think until the end, there wasn't really a way to really figure out how to actually use this in an efficient way.
因此，实际上确实很困难。我认为直到最后，实际上并没有真正弄清楚如何以有效的方式实际使用它的方法。
So, what I said was, what if we, like, change the design such that we include, sorry, next
所以，我说的是，如果我们喜欢改变设计，该怎么办，对不起，下一个
slide, no, yeah.
幻灯片，不，是的。
We let one proposer create all these shards and the beacon block.
我们让一个提议者创建所有这些碎片和信标块。
And then we only have one big committee that checks for all of these, whether this is valid
然后，我们只有一个大委员会检查所有这些，是否有效
or not.
或不。
can do that because when you have one pro one proposer um then we can just like we can just
可以做到这一点，因为当您有一个Pro一个建议者um时，我们可以像我们一样
look at all of them together and the reason for that is that if they fail to publish the data for
一起查看它们，原因是，如果他们未能发布数据
one of the shards um then we can just let the block fail that's their responsibility they
一个碎片之一，我们可以让障碍失败，这是他们的责任
up whereas when you have many different proposals you can't be that harsh because you can't
上升，而当您有许多不同的建议时，您不能那么苛刻，因为您不能
punish the proposer for shot one if the proposer for shot two did something bad um but when you're
如果枪击的提议者对两个枪手做得不好，但是当你你
when you aggregate the responsibility like that, then you can do it.
当您汇总这样的责任时，就可以做到。
And the important reason why we figured out we could do that is because
我们想知道我们这样做的重要原因是因为
in the process of researching MEV, we noticed that the ultimate equilibrium was something
在研究MEV的过程中，我们注意到最终的平衡是
like that anyway. It was very likely that blocks would be built quite centrally by some parties,
无论如何那样。某些各方很可能会在集中建造街区，
and that our whole design would be around containing the problems with that anyway.
而且，我们的整个设计都将包含问题。
So maintaining censorship resistance and making sure that they were honest and so on,
因此，保持抵制审查制度并确保他们诚实等等，
that was already on the roadmap anyway due to MEV.
由于MEV，这已经在路线图上。
And so it made sense to just say, well, we can get rid of all this complexity
因此，只要说，我们可以摆脱所有这些复杂性是很有意义的
of having all these many proposals because in reality it will be one anyway.
拥有所有这些建议，因为实际上它将是一个建议。
And we just need to contain the potential centralization vectors that come from that.
而且，我们只需要包含来自其中的潜在集中量向量即可。
Right, and so this is like the extension of that.
是的，这就像延伸一样。
So basically what happens is that in the world
因此，基本上发生的是世界上
of proposal builder separation,
提案建设者分离，
you would always come get a,
你总是会得到一个，
sorry, we are still on the previous slide.
抱歉，我们仍在上一个幻灯片上。
You would always get first a proposal block
您总是会首先获得提案块
where a proposal selects a builder
提案选择建筑商的地方
and that can be like just a small validator.
这就像一个小验证器一样。
They don't need a lot of hardware to compute that,
他们不需要很多硬件来计算这一点，
but then the main block would be built by a builder
但是，然后主要块将由建筑商建造
who has more resources and is able to construct
谁有更多的资源，并且能够构建
the beacon block and all the shard blocks at the same time.
信标块和所有碎片块同时。
There's one more ingredients that's with
还有一种成分
the dank sharding design and that is the idea
潮湿的设计，这就是想法
of having a two-dimensional polynomial extension.
具有二维多项式扩展。
And so the idea here is that we can,
因此，这里的想法是我们可以
So, we take the KZG commitments for the rows, and these are essentially the shards, or like
因此，我们采取KZG对行的承诺，这些承诺本质上是碎片，或者喜欢
I think in more modern speak, we would say blob, we would call them blobs, and each of
我认为，在更现代的说话中，我们会说斑点，我们称它们为斑点，每一个
them represents like a bit of data, but then it is extended as we discussed before.
它们像一些数据一样表示，但随后像我们之前讨论过。
So each line will be essentially one polynomial with an extension.
因此，每条线本质上都是一个多项式，并具有延伸。
But what we do in addition, we also extend them on the vertical axis.
但是，我们还要做的事情还将它们扩展到垂直轴上。
So each cell here will be extended down as well.
因此，这里的每个单元格也将延伸。
And the nice thing about KCG commitments is because they are linear, you can compute the
KCG承诺的好处是因为它们是线性的，您可以计算
additional KCG commitments just using a pretty normal extension as well.
额外的KCG承诺也仅使用非常普通的扩展名。
And doing this has some important advantages.
这样做有一些重要的优势。
So basically, the cool thing about that is that we can reconstruct the data if we have
因此，基本上，很酷的事情是，如果我们有
any 3 quarters of this whole square.
整个广场的任何三个季度。
It doesn't matter which one, but you can also do it in a distributed way.
哪一个都没关系，但是您也可以以分布式的方式进行操作。
And so we basically have two layers of validation here.
因此，我们基本上在这里有两层验证。
And one is first the validators will validate that the original.
首先是验证者将验证该原件。
So you can use the next slide.
因此，您可以使用下一张幻灯片。
With the validators will validate that the builder has done their work correctly.
使用验证者将验证建筑商的工作正确。
And they can do that by just downloading, in this example, two rows and two columns.
他们只需下载两个行和两列即可通过下载来做到这一点。
And if they do that, then if the blocks are unavailable, so less than 75% of the data is available, they can never get more than 1 16th of the validators voting for it.
而且，如果他们这样做，那么如果块不可用，因此不到75％的数据可用，他们将永远无法获得超过16的验证者投票。
So 1 16th of the attestations, which means that the block will basically be re-auged and ignored if it's not available.
因此，第1 16个证明，这意味着如果没有可用的话，基本上将重新忽略并忽略该块。
So as long as there's an honest majority, the validators would never vote for that block, which is always a good property to have.
因此，只要有诚实的多数，验证者就永远不会投票赞成该区块，这始终是一个好的财产。
Although we do not want to rely on the honest majority
尽管我们不想依靠诚实的多数
it's the first step that someone needs to get past.
这是某人需要过去的第一步。
Next slide.
下一个幻灯片。
What is like a nice additional property of that
那是一个很好的附加属性
is that because each row and each column individually
是因为每行和每一列单独
is a Reed-Solomon code or a polynomial,
是芦苇 - 固体代码或多项式，
they can be individually reconstructed.
它们可以单独重建。
So as soon as you have 50% of one row or one column,
因此，一旦您拥有一行或一列的50％，
you can reconstruct that row or column.
您可以重建该行或列。
And so this can happen completely in a completely distributed way.
因此，这可以完全分布的方式完全发生。
There has to be no super node or anything to reconstruct all the data.
必须没有超级节点或任何其他数据来重建所有数据。
This can happen in a very distributed way.
这可以以非常分布的方式发生。
Next slide.
下一个幻灯片。
And then the last step is, obviously, we want safety in the face of even a malicious majority.
然后，最后一步是，即使是恶意的多数，我们也希望安全。
And so this works using the, using data will be sampling.
因此，使用数据将使用该方法进行采样。
And what each node, each node will do
以及每个节点，每个节点都会执行
is they will choose like 75 random samples in the square
他们会在广场中选择75个随机样品吗
and they will don't know them.
他们不会认识他们。
And only if they find all of these samples,
只有当他们找到所有这些样本时，
will they say that it's all 75
他们会说这是75
because we actually need 75% of the samples
因为我们实际上需要75％的样品
in order to reconstruct the data,
为了重建数据，
which is higher than our one-deal threshold.
高于我们的一通阈值。
And so this again assures that it's available.
因此，这再次确保了它可用。
The probability of an unavailable block passing
不可用的块通过的概率
is less than two to the minus 30.
小于SINUS 30。
Cool.
凉爽的。
So let's quickly talk about how EIP-4844,
因此，让我们快速谈论EIP-4844如何
which you hopefully have heard about,
您希望听说过，
upgrade a couple of weeks ago,
几周前升级
I think it's interesting to this.
我认为这很有趣。
So if you look at Ethereum's data availability,
因此，如果您查看以太坊的数据可用性，
roll up so yesterday as in before yeah before it for for roll-ups got got data
昨天卷起，就像以前一样，是的，以获取数据
will be through call data which it was really expensive and really annoying and
将通过呼叫数据，这真的很昂贵且非常烦人，并且
since the 13th of March and we added blobs and so far only three blobs to the
自3月13日以来，我们在
to the blockchain that now roll-ups can use
到现在可以使用的区块链
in order to get cheaper data available on Ethereum.
为了获取以太坊上可用的廉价数据。
And then in the future, we will further extend this,
然后将来，我们将进一步扩展这一点，
so there will probably be some extensions
因此可能会有一些扩展
to AP-44 coming end of this year,
到今年年底，AP-44
or maybe sometime next year,
也许明年的某个时候
and then hopefully within the next two years or so,
然后希望在接下来的两年左右的时间内
we will get full sharding
我们将获得完整的碎片
with lots of data availability on Ethereum.
具有以太坊的大量数据可用性。
So the EIP-4844 design is very simple.
因此，EIP-4844设计非常简单。
We added to each block some KCG commitments to data,
我们在每个块中添加了一些KCG对数据的承诺，
and the actual data to these KCG commitments
以及这些KCG承诺的实际数据
is the block data, and that is just separately distributed
是块数据，这只是分开分布
on the network, which means we can be
在网络上，这意味着我们可以
a little bit more efficient, it can work in parallel,
效率更高，可以并行工作，
but everyone still gets all the data.
但是每个人仍然可以获得所有数据。
So it's not scalable yet, it's just like some
因此，它还不可扩展，就像有些
efficiency improvements around scooting data,
踏板数据周围的效率提高，
and in particular it starts a new data market.
特别是它开始了一个新的数据市场。
So like the main thing is,
如此主要的是，
they are now priced independently from execution.
他们现在的价格独立于执行。
It's a new gas type, which is cool,
这是一种新的气体类型，很酷，
because so far the ROABs always had to compete
因为到目前为止，Roabs总是必须竞争
with the layer one transactions,
在第一层交易中，
and that unfortunately often made it very expensive,
不幸的是，这常常使它变得非常昂贵，
because the price for those tended to be quite high,
因为那些人​​的价格往往很高，所以
and gas had to be priced,
而且汽油必须定价，
sorry, data has to be priced in a very pessimistic way.
抱歉，数据必须以非常悲观的方式定价。
That meant, yeah, that we were quite limited.
是的，我们非常有限。
And so you can see if you look at like L2 fees or something,
因此，您可以查看是否查看L2费用之类的东西，
now we have massively reduced the fees for roll-ups,
现在，我们已经大大降低了汇总的费用，
which is like a great achievement.
这就像一个伟大的成就。
Blobs are never required to compute the state updates.
从不需要斑点来计算状态更新。
So in order to like see what the latest state
因此，为了看最新状态
of the Ethereum chain is,
以太坊链是
you do not need the actual blob data.
您不需要实际的斑点数据。
only need that to know that they exist.
只需要知道它们存在。
And so the whole idea is that we designed this so that we can make all our future upgrades
因此，整个想法是我们设计了这个，以便我们可以进行所有未来的升级
quite easily.
很容易。
So in particular, we already use KCG commitments, and this means that we can directly upgrade
因此，特别是，我们已经使用KCG承诺，这意味着我们可以直接升级
this to use erasure coding.
这是使用擦除编码。
Like right now, we don't use erasure coding in any way, but it's very easily possible
像现在一样，我们不以任何方式使用擦除编码，但很容易
to add this.
添加此。
So almost all the work that we need to do can be done without consensus changes.
因此，我们几乎可以完成我们需要做的所有工作，而无需共识的改变。
The only thing that really ConsenSys needs to do in the future is update the number of
将来真正共识需要做的唯一的事情是更新
blobs that we can support.
我们可以支持的斑点。
And so that's really nice, because it really decouples this, and basically we can start
所以这真的很好，因为它确实使它脱离了，基本上我们可以开始
working on the whole networking and DAS and so on, without having to make lots of more
在整个网络和DAS上工作等等，而无需做更多的事情
upgrades to Ethereum.
升级到以太坊。
And the last cool thing is that rollups will not have to upgrade again to benefit.
最后一个很酷的事情是，汇总将不必再次升级才能受益。
So the interface to 4844 will stay completely the same through all the sharding upgrades.
因此，通过所有分片升级，到4844的接口将完全保持不变。
So if they start using blobs now, then hopefully a couple of years from now, they will have massive data availability from full-dank sharding.
因此，如果他们现在开始使用斑点，那么希望从现在开始几年后，他们将从全层次碎片中获得大量数据可用性。
All right.
好的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
And yeah, let me know if you have any questions.
是的，如果您有任何疑问，请告诉我。
Awesome.
惊人的。
Thank you so much, Dankorat.
非常感谢，Dankorat。
Yeah, very well.
是的，很好。
Yeah, thank you so much for your talk.
是的，非常感谢您的谈话。
I really appreciate it.
我真的很感激。
it was very insightful. I believe that we learned a lot. And folks, if you have any
这是非常有见地的。我相信我们学到了很多。伙计们，如果你有
questions for DynCraft, please write it in the Discord thread and we will ask shortly.
关于Dyncraft的问题，请将其写在Discord主题中，我们很快就会询问。
Yeah, I wanted to ask, yeah, there's a question, if you can elaborate a bit more about the current
是的，我想问，是的，有一个问题，您是否可以详细说明有关电流的更多信息
state, the current steps and challenges. So you mentioned there are some upgrades to be done on
声明，当前的步骤和挑战。所以你提到有一些升级可以完成
for it before, like the average recording and then the path to the full sharding.
因为它以前，就像平均记录一样，然后是通往完整碎片的路径。
So yeah, what are the problems, the challenges being solved right now to achieve that?
是的，有什么问题，现在解决的挑战是为了实现这一目标吗？
So with 4844, I mean, there are some things we would like to do.
因此，有了4844，我的意思是，我们想做一些事情。
I'm not actually fully looking at these at the moment.
目前，我实际上还没有完全看待这些。
I think currently we're mainly seeing how it all works.
我认为目前，我们主要看到一切工作原理。
I think there were some very minor problems,
我认为有一些非常小的问题，
but I think mainly it's the idea of watching it
但我认为这主要是观看它的想法
and over the next year,
明年，
hopefully we can just increase the number of blobs on it.
希望我们能增加其中的斑点数量。
I think when it comes to sharding,
我认为在碎片方面
there are definitely some pretty big hurdles
肯定有一些很大的障碍
that we still need to take.
我们仍然需要接受。
So, pool DAS is a departure from basically
因此，池Das基本上是一个偏离的
the networking model that currently all blockchains use.
当前所有区块链都使用的网络模型。
Currently blockchains typically operate on broadcasting.
目前，区块链通常在广播上运行。
Like basically it's like everyone sees everything,
就像基本上一样，就像每个人都看到的一切一样，
all the messages on the network.
网络上的所有消息。
And with DAS, we want a much thinner network.
使用DAS，我们想要一个更薄的网络。
We want to be able to like,
我们希望能够喜欢
have only a very small number of nodes store each sample.
每个样品只有很少的节点存储。
And that prevents a big challenge in the face of, yeah, possible attacks and so on.
这防止了面对可能的攻击等等，这阻止了巨大的挑战。
So, like, the possible networking constructions.
因此，就像可能的网络结构。
We do have some, like, we do have a pretty good idea on how to get, like, a medium amount of scaling.
我们确实有一些，就像如何获得相当数量的缩放率有关。
So, basically, there's a construction that we already worked on, which is called PeerDAS.
因此，基本上，我们已经在研究了一种结构，称为Peerdas。
So, if you scale it to the extent that pretty much all samples are still in your networking vicinity,
因此，如果您将其扩展到几乎所有样本仍在您的网络附近的程度，则
as in like within one hop of your node,
就像在您的节点的一个跳跃中一样
then you can still be pretty safe
那你仍然可以很安全
and everything kind of works as it does now.
一切都可以正常工作。
So that's pretty nice.
所以很好。
So this will be our first step.
因此，这将是我们的第一步。
And I think like the next step going to full sharding,
而且我认为就像下一步进入完整的碎片一样，
that's still somewhat of a bigger question.
这仍然是一个更大的问题。
Well, I mean, you basically, it is quite achievable
好吧，我的意思是，您基本上是可以实现的
if you're on board another security assumption
如果您在其他安全性假设上
where you basically say, hey, I'm happy to trust that
您基本上说，嘿，我很高兴相信
There will be some super nodes who always keep all the samples, and as long as one of
会有一些超级节点总是保留所有样本，只要一个
those super nodes is honest, everything will work fine.
那些超级节点是诚实的，一切都会好起来的。
And I think that's a relatively okay assumption to make, but many people are not too comfortable
我认为这是一个相对可以的假设，但是许多人不太舒服
with it.
与它。
But yeah, with that assumption, you can relatively work.
但是，是的，有了这个假设，您可以相对工作。
That's what basically Celestia is doing.
这就是Celestia在做的事情。
It works for them.
它对他们有用。
I think once you go to a fully distributed system
我认为一旦您进入了一个完全分布式系统
and also DHT, there's still actual research
还有DHT，仍然有实际的研究
to be done at the moment.
目前要完成。
Interesting, thank you very much.
有趣的是，非常感谢。
Awesome.
惊人的。
Yeah, there's a question about the 2d KZG.
是的，关于2D KZG有一个问题。
Where the number 75% is coming from,
数字75％来自哪里，
whether it's 50% of the data for polimodal reconstruction
是否是多型重建数据的50％
but multiplied by two, or?
但是乘以两个，还是？
No it's it simply comes if you solve so you want you you want 75 percent of the samples to be
不，如果您解决的话，它只是想让您希望75％的样本成为
available so you need 0.75 to the power of n to be 2 to the minus 30 and then you get 75 roughly.
可用，因此您需要0.75的n功率为230，然后大致获得75。
Cool, cool, cool.
凉爽，凉爽，凉爽。
Yeah, Fox, if you have more questions, please go ahead and ask.
是的，福克斯，如果您还有更多问题，请继续询问。
Are there any drawbacks for the insurance, from a security perspective or protocol perspective,
从安全的角度或协议的角度来看，保险是否有任何缺点，
any trade-offs that you think there are?
您认为有任何权衡吗？
terms of usage, in terms of like for the roll-ups? For the protocol, for
使用条款，就卷起吗？对于协议
like the security, like for example, there was a lot of chat about issues with
像安全性一样，例如，与
bandwidth. Right, yeah, I mean, bandwidth has increased, so this is true it's
带宽。是的，是的，我的意思是，带宽有所增加，所以这是真的
actually still, I think it's it's an interesting issue, because yeah, there
实际上，我认为这是一个有趣的问题，因为是的，
were some other issues with Tenkuun, where like, there were some
还有Tenkuun的其他问题，就像在哪里
bugs in the client software that increased bandwidth for completely different reasons.
客户软件中的错误由于完全不同的原因而增加带宽。
So I think a lot of validators saw a high bandwidth increase that actually is not caused
因此，我认为许多验证者看到的带宽很高，实际上并非引起
by the blobs, but by the attestation aggregation gossip.
通过斑点，但通过证明聚集八卦。
Yeah, I mean, I think, yes, it is a bandwidth increase.
是的，我的意思是，我想，是的，这是带宽的增加。
I think, yeah, to an extent, yeah, we need to figure out what we're comfortable with.
是的，在某种程度上，是的，我们需要弄清楚我们对什么感到满意。
I think, yes, there will always be a trade-off where some people will say, well, this is now too much for me.
我认为，是的，总会有一个权衡，有人会说，现在对我来说太多了。
I think, I hope very soon we will have constructions that will reduce the bandwidth a bit that you need.
我认为，我希望很快我们将拥有可以减少您需要的带宽的结构。
But there is also, yeah, there are ways to reduce the networking itself.
但是，是的，有一些方法可以减少网络本身。
So there's lots of optimizations that can be done at the moment.
因此，目前可以进行许多优化。
Cool, cool. Thank you so much.
酷，很酷。太感谢了。
Yeah, there's a question about the data availability sampling, specifically the mechanism for identifying whether the node is storing the data honestly and how they will be slashed.
是的，关于数据可用性采样的问题，特别是用于识别节点是否诚实存储数据以及如何削减数据的机制。
So if, I assume there's some kind of challenge,
因此，如果我认为存在某种挑战，
but what if the node is, for example,
但是，如果节点是，例如
offline and acting honestly,
离线和诚实行事，
just whether we have some mechanism for this, yeah.
只是我们是否有一些机制，是的。
Right, so you cannot slash nodes, right?
是的，所以您不能砍伐节点，对吗？
Nodes are not bonded, so there's nothing really
节点不是绑定的，所以没有什么
that you can do.
你可以做。
So nodes can just store the data or not.
因此，节点可以存储数据是否存储。
You can, if it's one of your peers,
您可以，如果这是您的同行之一，
So that's one of the advantages if you have a very local system
因此，如果您有一个非常本地的系统，那就是优势之一
and it's on VPS, then you can downscore them.
它在VPS上，然后您可以降低它们。
You can say, if you don't have a sample that I think you're supposed to have,
您可以说，如果您没有我认为您应该拥有的样本，
then you're not a great peer.
那你不是一个很好的同伴。
So I might downscore you, and if your score is too low,
所以我可能会降低您的范围，如果您的分数太低，
I'm going to disconnect it from you.
我将与您断开连接。
So this is a possibility for storage.
因此，这是存储的可能性。
So currently, we don't really have any expert storage mechanisms.
因此，目前，我们真的没有任何专家存储机制。
And this is, by the way, not a change in Ethereum.
顺便说一下，这不是以太坊的变化。
This has also been the case.
情况也是如此。
Nobody guarantees that past Ethereum blocks are kept as storage.
没有人保证过去的以太坊块被保存为存储空间。
It just happens to be the default node implementation.
恰好是默认节点实现。
We will, in the future, probably include a construction that is called a proof custody.
将来，我们将包括一种称为证明监护权的建筑。
That basically means that validators at least have to store it for a while in order not to be slashed.
这基本上意味着验证者至少必须存储一段时间才能不被削减。
This is a future upgrade.
这是未来的升级。
That's probably a few years from now because it's not the highest priority at the moment.
从现在开始大概是几年了，因为目前还不是最高的优先事项。
This will not directly help if data will be sampling.
如果数据将进行采样，这将无法直接帮助。
Like, individual samples, because, like, you can't really, like, yes,
就像单个样本一样，因为，就像，您无法真正，喜欢，是的，
Ethereum doesn't really want slashing conditions that are really short-term.
以太坊并不真正想要真正短期的削减条件。
Like if you don't answer within 10 seconds, you get slashed.
就像您在10秒内不回答一样，您就会被砍掉。
Like that's pretty anti-Ethereum.
像那样的是反省。
Like it doesn't really work because like, for example,
就像它真的没有用，因为例如
validators, we want that you're able to run them from home.
验证者，我们希望您能够在家中运行它们。
You can have a bad internet connection and so on.
您可以拥有不良的互联网连接，依此类推。
So all these things are pretty long-term
所以所有这些都是长期的
and aren't really like to do with,
而且不是真的很喜欢
can I get my samples right now?
我现在可以获取样品吗？
So you really need like, yeah,
所以你真的需要，是的，
this is one of the difficult things that you really need
这是您真正需要的困难之一
to rely on honest nodes a lot.
经常依靠诚实的节点。
and that's what makes sampling itself difficult.
这就是使抽样本身变得困难的原因。
Awesome, it's very interesting.
太棒了，这很有趣。
I didn't realize that you can use DAS
我没有意识到你可以使用DAS
to score your peers.
为您的同龄人评分。
That can be very effective.
那可能非常有效。
Yeah, it's interesting.
是的，很有趣。
Yeah, folks, please feel free to ask more questions.
是的，伙计们，请随时提出更多问题。
We have some more time with Dan Kradt,
我们和丹·克拉德（Dan Kradt）有更多时间
so it's an opportunity to pick his brain.
因此，这是一个捡大脑的机会。
I would maybe ask something more general
我可能会问一些更笼统的事情
outside of the, even outside of, like, the sharding
在外面，甚至在碎片之外
is a very, very exciting topic,
是一个非常非常令人兴奋的话题
of course. Are there any other domains
当然。还有其他域
that you find interesting, exciting, which
您发现有趣，令人兴奋的
you've been working on recently, maybe even outside
您最近一直在工作，甚至可能在外面
of Ethereum?
以太坊？
Right.
正确的。
I mean, inside Ethereum,
我的意思是，在以太坊内，
I think, like, one of the big
我认为，大个子之一
things that,
东西，
yeah, like, currently
是的，现在，目前
I think a lot of people are thinking about
我认为很多人正在考虑
is the economics, so
是经济学，所以
it's, like, a pretty big topic.
这是一个非常重要的话题。
I think, like,
我认为，就像
everyone is trying to wrap their head around
每个人都试图缠绕着自己的头
what staking could look like in the future.
将来可能的样子。
I think it doesn't
我认为不是
seem ideal that all the stake is grabbed by liquid staking tokens, and so we're trying
似乎理想的所有股份都被液体含有代币抓住，所以我们正在尝试
to figure out if there is any way in which
找出是否有任何方法
that is not the case.
事实并非如此。
Yeah, so a lot of thoughts around that.
是的，对此有很多想法。
otherwise
否则
yeah, I mean
是的，我的意思是
no, I don't have any
不，我没有
like
喜欢
I mean, many of my
我的意思是，我的许多
much of my research at the moment
目前我的大部分研究
is trying to get
试图得到
sharding implemented and working all around those
分碎实施并围绕这些实施
Awesome
惊人的
maybe you kind of
也许你有点
mentioned the staking there and you had a bit
提到那里的赌场，你有点
on the staking maximalism
在Staking Maximalism上
liquid staking maximalism
液体存在最大主义
Maybe if you can talk a bit about that.
也许如果您可以谈论一下。
Right, I mean, I think, so this was something I posted on Twitter, I think, sometime last year.
是的，我的意思是，我认为，所以这是我在Twitter上发布的，我认为去年的某个时候。
It was really, I think, a very, try to think, very blue sky thinking, and I don't think it's a great idea.
我认为，这确实是一个非常蓝天的思考，我认为这不是一个好主意。
But the idea was that what's, I think, like, especially in the Cosmos Solana ecosystems,
但是我的想法是，我认为，尤其是在宇宙索拉纳生态系统中，
a lot of people think of, oh, staking doesn't really, like, issuance to stakers is not really
很多人想到的是，对Stakers的发行并不是真的，并不是真的
real issuance, because everyone can stake.
真正的发行，因为每个人都可以利用。
So you, like, essentially, in the end, it becomes just, like, everyone stakes, and then
因此，从本质上讲，您最终，它变成了每个人的赌注，然后
everyone is rewarded for it.
每个人都为此得到回报。
So it's like a complete zero-sum game.
因此，这就像一个完整的零和游戏。
and obviously
显然
like in all of these they are based on
像所有这些一样
delegated proof of stake
委托书证明
and I mean in a certain way
我的意思是以某种方式
it is like an appealing thing to think
思考就像一件吸引人的事情
like oh like maybe that solves all of
就像哦，也许可以解决所有
our problems if we could just like
如果我们能喜欢的话，我们的问题
just make delegation the primary
只是使委派成为主要
way to stake and
赌注和
I try to think about that
我尝试考虑
I think like
我想喜欢
Vitalik first like basically
Vitalik首先像基本上一样
the end result is always like, why?
最终结果总是喜欢，为什么？
What do we get out of it?
我们从中得到什么？
Like, how do these stakers help us?
像，这些stakers对我们有何帮助？
And it's not really clear.
而且还不清楚。
Unfortunately it's hard.
不幸的是，这很难。
In many of these cases it feels like staking simply
在许多情况下，感觉就像是放在
becomes just like a pure money game,
就像一个纯粹的钱游戏一样
and there's nothing actually in it for the protocol.
协议中没有什么实际上没有。
So then why are we even doing it?
那为什么我们甚至这样做呢？
So yeah, currently.
是的，目前。
I don't completely know.
我不完全知道。
I think it is interesting to think about all these proposals.
我认为考虑所有这些建议很有趣。
I'm not currently very strongly leaning in any direction.
我目前并不是很靠任何方向倾斜。
I think what I mainly feel these days is that we need to just keep staking more limited.
我认为这些天我的主要感觉是，我们需要继续保持更加有限。
it. I think the most dangerous scenario I see these days is if all of all Ether is staked.
它。我认为这些天我看到的最危险的情况是，如果所有以太都被固定在上面。
I feel like that's very hard to reverse. We end up in a world where everyone is suddenly
我觉得这很难逆转。我们最终进入了一个每个人突然突然的世界
literally a stakeholder, and so nobody wants their income reduced. Obviously, that influences
从字面上看，一个利益相关者，因此没有人希望他们的收入减少。显然，这会影响
people's decision making. All of Ethereum governance would now be about, oh, how many
人们的决策。现在，所有以太坊治理都将是关于多少
percent that I'm making on this and so on. So that seems pretty dangerous and dystopian world. So
我在此上赚的百分比等等。因此，这似乎很危险和反乌托邦世界。所以
I think along those lines, but yes, we don't have the solution yet, unfortunately.
我认为沿着这些线路，但是，不幸的是，我们还没有解决方案。
Thank you. That's very interesting though. Thanks for sharing that.
谢谢。那很有趣。感谢您分享。
it. And yeah, maybe also on the topic of staking, what's your feeling on when a protocol has
它。是的，也许也是关于签名的话题，您对协议有什么感觉
enough economic security?
足够的经济安全？
Right, I'm actually a fairly a minimalist on economic security. I don't believe that.
是的，我实际上是对经济安全的极简主义者。我不相信。
I think honestly, between one and 10 billion or so, it's all the economic security you'll
老实说，我认为，一到100亿左右，这是所有的经济安全
ever need. I think we have way more than is necessary already. I don't think that an attacker,
曾经需要。我认为我们的路超过了必要的。我不认为是攻击者，
this is basically the front door. I think the front door, acquiring enough stake to do something
这基本上是前门。我认为前门，获得足够的股份来做某事
bad to Ethereum is already so secure that no attacker will try to attack it. If I had a billion
对以太坊的不利已经是如此安全，以至于没有攻击者会尝试攻击它。如果我有十亿
dollars or it let's rather say yes like assume that ethereum's economic security was only in
美元否则让我们说是的，就像假设以太坊的经济安全仅在
quotation marks 10 billion dollars now in order to attack you realistically say would need i don't
报价标志着现在有100亿美元
know let's say it's three billion dollars or five let's say it's five to get one third so not really
知道是说是三十亿美元还是五个，是说要获得三分之一，所以不是真的
like that but like let's say where this is not how it would use five billion dollars to attack
像这样，但就像说这不是在哪里使用50亿美元攻击的方式
Ethereum for sure, just in order to basically perform one double finalization.
以太坊肯定，只是为了基本上执行一个双重命运。
That seems, I do not think that the double finalization will do that much damage
看来，我认为双重最终确定会造成太大的损害
and I believe also that there are other potential vectors that are much, much cheaper.
而且我也相信，还有其他潜在的向量更便宜。
Think about how many zero days you can purchase for five million dollars.
考虑一下您可以购买五百万美元的零天数。
So I think like, yeah, I think we are far beyond the point where we need more economic security.
因此，我认为，是的，我认为我们远远超出了我们需要更多经济安全的地步。
That's really cool. Yeah, it's this really great point about that basically other bottlenecks when
那真的很酷。是的，这是关于其他基本上其他瓶颈真的很棒的
when the economy security is growing.
当经济安全增长时。
That's a good point there.
那是一个很好的点。
Yeah, thank you so much.
是的，非常感谢。
Okay.
好的。
I'm curious if you can elaborate a little bit
我很好奇您是否可以详细说明
on what it looks like in a world where all ether is staked.
在一个全部固定的世界中，它的样子。
What?
什么？
Like what are the conditions that like bring this into being?
就像将其变成的条件是什么？
Right.
正确的。
So, right.
所以，对。
So basically, I mean, the main thing is so like, for, to understand that we have to think
因此，基本上，我的意思是，主要的事情是如此，要理解我们必须思考
about like what happens with liquid staking tokens, right?
关于液体含有令牌会发生什么，对吗？
So, so people like originally people stake because like they want, um, a certain amount
因此，因此人们喜欢原本人的股份，因为像他们想要的那样，嗯，一定数量
of, like, they get a certain amount of reward for, um, essentially two things, like they
就像他们获得了一定的回报，嗯，本质上是两件事，就像他们一样
lock up their money as a security so they lock up ether which means they can't use it like immediately
将他们的钱锁定为安全性，因此他们锁定以太币
um and uh and they have to like run a ballot or something and so liquid staking in a way like
嗯，嗯，他们必须喜欢投票或其他东西，所以液体以类似
um gets rid of that to a certain extent so you don't need to run your invalid it
嗯，在一定程度上摆脱了这一点，因此您不需要运行无效的
anymore you get a little bit less reward and someone else runs it
再过，您获得的奖励少一些，其他人运行它
it. And it does a few things. So it gets rid of the capital bottleneck. So like, okay.
它。它做了一些事情。因此，它摆脱了资本瓶颈。好吧，好吧。
And yeah, the other thing it does is that it allows you to get out immediately as long
是的，它的另一件事是，它可以让您立即离开
as there's enough liquidity. Well, and this is the third thing, like you can also, yeah,
因为有足够的流动性。好吧，这是第三件事，就像您还可以，是的，
it is that that's kind of a function of liquidity as well, but yeah, you can also use it. Like,
这也是流动性的函数，但是，您也可以使用它。喜欢，
example in DeFi you can lock it up to do other things and so on and what can happen is like
示例在defi中您可以锁定去做其他事情，依此类推，可能发生的事情是
at a certain point if there is like enough liquid liquidity in liquid staking tokens
在某个时刻，是否有足够的液体流动性在液体含有代币中
they could become so attractive that the reward is almost irrelevant like let's say
他们可能会变得如此吸引人，以至于奖励几乎是无关紧要的，就像可以说
Lido staked Ether
丽托（Lido）固定了以太
had all the same functions
具有相同的功能
as Ethereum itself.
作为以太坊本身。
And people literally
和人们字面上
on exchanges
在交流上
started trading
开始交易
like LS Ether
像LS Ether
instead of Ether.
而不是以太。
Right?
正确的？
So,
所以，
sorry, Steve.
对不起，史蒂夫。
what's the difference now?
现在有什么区别？
Well, the difference is that
好吧，区别在于
like Lido staked Ether
像利多·汤匙的ether
still has like a yield
仍然有产量
compared to Ethereum.
与以太坊相比。
So it would always be
所以永远是
like if everything else
就像其他一切
is the same,
是一样的，
it will always be more attractive.
它将永远更具吸引力。
And that's then even true if the rewards go down to 1% or 0.5% or less.
如果奖励下降到1％或0.5％或更少，那就是事实。
So there's a potential runaway scenario here
所以这里有一个潜在的失控场景
where even with extremely low yields,
即使产量极低，
they could basically eat up everything.
他们基本上可以吃掉一切。
And the only thing that Ether would still be used on
唯一仍然可以使用以太的东西
would be directly paying for gas.
将直接支付汽油。
That's still true.
仍然是真的。
You have to ultimately change to Ether in order to pay gas.
您必须最终更改为以太才能支付汽油。
But, I mean, probably, like, a reserve of a few percent of that is enough, like, as long as that's all allocated to DEXs where you can efficiently buy it exactly when you need it.
但是，我的意思是，只要所有这些都分配给了DEX，您可能会储备几％，就像在需要时可以有效地购买它。
So, yeah, that's a scenario where it could be that, like, basically all ETH becomes staked.
所以，是的，这是一种场景，就像基本上所有的ETH都被粘住了。
We're currently not there yet.
我们目前还没有。
We clearly, like, are not seeing the extreme, like, staking pressures that we saw last year.
我们显然没有看到我们去年看到的极端压力。
It stopped at some point.
它在某个时候停止了。
I think we're seeing a little bit more staking again, but we're still not in a runaway scenario.
我认为我们再次看到更多的赌注，但是我们仍然没有处于失控的情况。
So people still want something like 3% to 4% yield on their staked ETH.
因此，人们仍然希望将其固定的ETH产量约3％至4％。
And it makes sense because right now the main liquid token is still Ether.
这是有道理的，因为现在主要的液体令牌仍然是以太。
Like if, for example, you're thinking about cashing out during the bull market,
例如，例如，您正在考虑在牛市上兑现，
you probably think about, okay, at some point I want Ether.
您可能会考虑一下，在某个时候我想要以太。
And what if at that point staked Ether trades at a discount,
如果那时以折扣的是将以太交易的交易，该怎么办？
then I would have to take that discount.
那我将不得不享受折扣。
That might not be worth the risk, right?
那可能不值得冒险，对吗？
So currently, we're still not at a point where people would be happy with a very small yield,
因此，目前，我们仍然不在一个人的收益率很小的时候感到满意
like less than 1%.
像小于1％。
But yeah, I can see that it could eventually happen.
但是，是的，我可以看到它最终可能发生。
I think that's what we are quite scared of.
我认为这就是我们非常害怕的。
Awesome. Thank you.
惊人的。谢谢。
Yeah, thank you.
是的，谢谢。
Um, okay, uh, if we can, if we can hold you for a minute longer, maybe, maybe a few more
嗯，好吧，嗯，如果可以的话，如果我们可以再等你一分钟，也许还有更多
questions.
问题。
Uh, there is, um, yeah, there's one about what are the common misconceptions about sharding?
嗯，嗯，是的，关于碎片的常见误解是什么？
What would be like some, you know, top misunderstanding that people often, uh, if you would like to
您知道，某些人会是什么样的误会，人们经常，如果您愿意的话
debunk?
揭穿？
So I think one fun thing is that sharding, or rather our modern version of sharding,
因此，我认为一件有趣的事情是碎片，或者是我们现代版本的碎片，
which is data sharding with rollups, necessarily means that there will be no more composability.
这是随着汇总的数据碎片，必然意味着将不再具有合成性。
So one cool thing is that rollups, and so back when we designed execution sharding,
因此，一件很酷的事情是汇总，因此当我们设计执行碎片时，请返回
yes, this was one of the huge problems we had with sharding.
是的，这是我们碎片遇到的巨大问题之一。
We're like, OK, every shard is its own little ecosystem.
好吧，我们想，每个碎片都是它自己的小生态系统。
And moving between shards would be definitely not synchronous.
在碎片之间移动绝对不会同步。
But with rollups, the case is actually a bit different
但是随着汇总，情况实际上有些不同
because you can design very big rollups.
因为您可以设计非常大的汇总。
I mean, Jesse from Bayes posted the other day,
我的意思是，贝丝的杰西（Jesse）前几天发布，
they want to scale to 1 giga gas per second, which is amazing,
他们想扩大每秒1千兆气的比例，这很棒，
which is exactly what rollups should do.
这正是汇总应该做的。
And the cool thing is that it's okay for rollups to do that
很酷的是，汇总可以做到这一点
because they do not have to be as decentralized as the base layer
因为它们不必像基础层那样分散
because they can be held accountable by the base layer.
因为它们可以通过基层负责。
Like, we can maintain their security
就像，我们可以保持他们的安全
and maintain their censorship resistance,
并保持其审查制度，
even if they don't, if they are built correctly.
即使他们不正确，也可以正确地构建。
Like, if their smart contracts have, like,
就像，如果他们的智能合约有
forced transactions with mechanisms, et cetera.
用机制的强制交易等。
So what is really cool is that within this rollup,
因此，真正很酷的是在此汇总中，
you can have massive ecosystems that internally
您可以拥有内部的大规模生态系统
have full composability.
具有完整的合成性。
To some extent, if you are willing to integrate
在某种程度上，如果您愿意整合
with the base layer proposals,
与基础层建议，
you can even have composability with the base layer
您甚至可以与基础层具有合成性
honestly care about it.
老实说。
Right, awesome, thank you, thank you.
对，太棒了，谢谢，谢谢。
Okay, we've, yeah, one question about more, so if you can give us some maybe more specific
好的，我们已经有一个问题，所以如果您可以给我们一些更具体的问题
open R&D problems around the data availability sampling and data development in general,
一般而言，围绕数据可用性采样和数据开发的开放研发问题，
maybe something that, you know, people can learn about, start contributing to, yeah,
也许，您知道，人们可以学习，开始为
many eager contributors here.
许多渴望的贡献者。
Right, yeah, concretely, the biggest open question is how to build a robust distributed
是的，是的，具体地，最大的开放问题是如何构建一个强大的分布
hash table or DHT.
哈希表或DHT。
So if anyone is interested in working on that, this is like one really interesting, really
因此，如果有人对此感兴趣，那就像一个非常有趣的
cool topic.
很酷的话题。
So one of the big problems with DHTs is like traditionally peer-to-peer networks have no
因此，DHT的最大问题之一就是传统上，对等网络没有
limitation on who can join as a node.
谁可以加入节点的限制。
And that is somewhat contained in, like, I mean, I mentioned this before,
这在某种程度上包含在我之前，我以前提到过
that for our usual blockchains like Ethereum, Bitcoin, everything is broadcast.
对于我们通常的区块链，例如以太坊，比特币，一切都是广播。
And if you rely on that, the cool thing is that you only have to assume
如果您依靠这一点，那么很酷的是您只需要假设
that you're connected to one honest node.
您已连接到一个诚实的节点。
And that's, like, a fairly acceptable assumption
这就是一个相当可接受的假设
that people are relatively comfortable with.
人们相对舒适。
and that makes it pretty hard,
这很难
even though you have this free joining mechanism,
即使您拥有这种免费的加入机制，
anyone can join.
任何人都可以加入。
It's quite hard.
很难。
You can potentially trick new nodes.
您可能会欺骗新节点。
It's very hard to trick nodes
很难欺骗节点
that are already well-connected in the network.
在网络中已经有很好的联系。
And so the problem with DHTs
因此DHT的问题
is that their security assumptions are much harder,
是他们的安全假设要困难得多，
and they break down even with relatively minor fractions
即使分数相对较小，它们即使分解
of malicious nodes, which we can't really guarantee
恶意节点，我们无法真正保证
because an attacker could literally just add
因为攻击者实际上可以添加
a million malicious nodes to the film network
电影网络的一百万个恶意节点
and we would have nothing we could do about it.
我们将无能为力。
So yeah, that's currently a problem that we have.
是的，这是我们目前遇到的问题。
If people want to work on this,
如果人们想为此努力
nobody has really found a great design yet
没有人真的找到了一个很棒的设计
that works in the face.
在脸上起作用。
it can work on similar assumptions as current P2P networks.
它可以使用与当前P2P网络相似的假设。
That's very interesting.
那很有趣。
Yeah, I hope some folks from the study group will look into that.
是的，我希望研究小组的一些人会研究一下。
And yeah, we are at 70-minute mark.
是的，我们的成绩为70分钟。
I think we can slowly be wrapping up.
我认为我们可以慢慢结束。
Josh, do we have any more questions?
乔什，我们还有其他问题吗？
Yeah, I'm curious if execution sharding is something that is on the roadmap at some
是的，我很好奇执行碎片是否是路线图上的东西
point and how that will differ from the data sharding.
要点及其与数据碎片的不同。
Yeah, I think nowadays I view execution sharding very differently.
是的，我认为如今我认为执行碎片的差异很大。
I think a lot of things have changed in the landscape in the last five years, and I would
我认为过去五年中的景观发生了很多事情，我会
say the way I see some form of execution sharding come back into Ethereum would be that we start
说出我看到某种形式的执行碎片回到以太坊的方式是我们开始
increasing the gas limit of the execution layer. The way we do that is by putting the execution
增加执行层的气体限制。我们这样做的方式是通过执行
layer itself onto our data layer and add proving through a zkv-evm to it. What we would have would
将自己分层到我们的数据层上，并通过ZKV-EVM添加证明。我们会的
be basically the base layer would itself become a roll-up in that full nodes don't have to verify it
基本上是基本层本身会成为一个滚动，因为完整节点不必验证它
it anymore.
它了。
And at that point, I think we can get to a point
到那时，我认为我们可以达到一定程度
where we can start scaling it itself.
我们可以在哪里开始缩放它。
It's probably not going to be as aggressive as roll-ups will.
这可能不会像卷起一样积极。
We will probably be a little bit more conservative.
我们可能会更加保守。
But I can see that we can get 100 or 1,000 x eventually
但是我可以看到我们最终可以得到100或1,000 x
out of the base layer as well.
也不在基层。
Great.
伟大的。
And yeah, the cool thing is it will remain fully composable
是的，很酷的事情是它将保持完全综合
because it's still just like one logical chart.
因为它仍然像一个逻辑图表。
Well, yeah, I think that's all the questions
好吧，是的，我认为这就是所有问题
that I see in here.
我在这里看到的。
Yeah, yeah, I think we are the questions already
是的，是的，我认为我们已经是问题了
and we are at more than 70 minutes.
我们已经超过70分钟了。
So yeah, it's enough of your time, Dankrat.
是的，丹克拉特（Dankrat）就足够了。
I know it's precious,
我知道这很宝贵，
and we really appreciate having you here.
我们非常感谢您在这里。
It's been an honor.
这是一种荣誉。
Yeah, it's been a pleasure.
是的，很高兴。
Yep.
是的。
Thank you for having me.
谢谢你有我。
Thank you so much, Dankrat.
非常感谢，Dankrat。
Yeah, we appreciate having you in the study group.
是的，我们感谢您加入研究小组。
We learned a lot,
我们学到了很多，
and I hope some folks will write a great documentation
我希望有些人会写一份很棒的文件
on our wiki and start talking
在我们的Wiki上开始说话
into the data availability sampling
进入数据可用性采样
and the related problems, yeah.
是的，是的。
yeah it would be great yeah thank you
是的，很好，谢谢
yes it's my yeah have a great day
是的，这是我的一天
bye-bye yeah you too but everyone and
再见是的，你们，但每个人都
we'll see you on Monday
我们星期一见
well uh yes see you on Monday for
好吧，是的，星期一见
another development track course with
另一个开发轨道课程
dragon I believe looking at execution
龙我相信看执行
client deep dive it's we will see will
客户深度潜水是我们将看到的
have Dragan, the developer, the lead developer of Red, if I'm not wrong, explaining the architecture
如果我没有错，请让开发人员，开发人员，红色的首席开发人员解释体系结构
of Red moving into the database. And if anybody's interested in Rust, in execution clients,
红色移入数据库。如果有人对Rust感兴趣，对执行客户
in Red specifically, this will be a great learning opportunity for you. Yeah. Awesome.
具体来说，这对您来说将是一个很好的学习机会。是的。惊人的。
See you then. Cool. Thank you, everybody. Bye.
然后见。凉爽的。谢谢大家。再见。